Chapter 65. The whale as a dish.
That mortal man should feed upon the creature that feeds his lamp, and like
Stub, eat him by his own light, as you may say. This seems so outlandish a
thing that one must needs go a little into the history and philosophy of it.
It is upon record that three centuries ago the tongue of the right whale was
esteemed a great delicacy in France and commanded large prices there.
Also that in Henry VII's time a certain cook of the court obtained a handsome
reward for inventing an admirable sauce to be eaten with barbecued porpuses
which you remember are a species of whale. Porpuses indeed are to this day
considered fine eating. The meat is made into balls about the size of billiard
balls and being well seasoned and spiced might be taken for turtle balls or ve
balls. The old monks of Dun Firmland were very fond of them. They had a great
porpus grant from the crown.
The fact is that among his hunters at least the whale would by all hands be
considered a noble dish were there not so much of him. But when you come to sit
down before a meat pie nearly 100 ft long, it takes away your appetite. Only
the most unprejudiced of men like Stub nowadays partake of cooked whales. But
the Eskimos are not so fidious. We all know how they live upon whales and have
rare old vintages of prime old train oil. Zoganda, one of their most famous
doctors, recommend strips of blubber for infants as being exceedingly juicy and
nourishing. And this reminds me that certain Englishmen who long ago were
accidentally left in Greenland by a whaling vessel, that these men actually
lived for several months on the moldy scraps of whales, which had been left
ashore after trying out the blubber.
Among the Dutch whalemen, these scraps are called fritters, which indeed they
greatly resemble, being brown and crisp, and smelling something like old
Amsterdam housewives donuts or oily cooks when fresh.
They have such an edible look that the most self-denying stranger can hardly keep his hands off.
But what further depreciates the whale as a civilized dish is his exceeding
richness. He is the great prize ox of the sea, too fat to be delicately good.
Look at his hump, which would be as fine eating as the buffaloos, which is
esteemed a rare dish, were it not such a solid pyramid of fat. But the spermaceti
itself, how bland and creamy that is, like the transparent half jellied white
meat of a coconut in the third month of its growth, yet far too rich to supply a
substitute for butter. Nevertheless, many whalemen have a method of absorbing
it into some other substance and then partaking of it. In the long triatches
of the night, it is a common thing for the seammen to dip their ship biscuit
into the huge oil pots and let them fry there a while. Many a good supper have I
thus made.
In the case of a small sperm whale, the brains are accounted a fine dish. The
casket of the skull is broken into with an axe and the two plump whitish lobes
being withdrawn precisely resembling two large puddings. They are then mixed with
flour and cooked into a most delectable mess in flavor somewhat resembling
calves heads which is quite a dish among some epicures. And everyone knows that
some young bucks among the epicures by continually dining upon cal's brains by
and by get to have a little brains of
their own so as to be able to tell a calf's head from their own heads which
indeed requires uncommon discrimination.
And that is the reason why a young buck with an intelligentlooking calf's head
before him is somehow one of the saddest sights you can see. The head looks a
sort of reproachfully at him with an etu brutee expression.
It is not perhaps entirely because the whale is so excessively anxious that
landsmen seem to regard the eating of him with abhorance. That appears to
result in some way from the consideration before mention, i.e. that
a man should eat a newly murdered thing of the sea and eat it too by its own
light. But no doubt the first man that ever murdered an ox was regarded as a
murderer. Perhaps he was hung, and if he had been put on his trial by oxen, he
certainly would have been, and he certainly deserved it, if any murderer
does. Go to the meat market of a Saturday night and see the crowds of
live bipeds staring up at the long rows of dead quadripeds.
Does not that sight take a tooth out of the cannibal's jaw? cannibals. Who is
not a cannibal? I tell you, it will be more tolerable for the Fiji that salted
down a lean missionary in his cellar against a coming famine. It will be more
tolerable for that provident Fiji, I say, in the day of judgment than for
thee, civilized and enlightened gourmand, who nail geese to the ground,
and feast on their bloated livers in thy pate deuagra.
But Stub, he eats the whale by its own light, does he? And that is adding
insult to injury, is it? Look at your knife handle there, my civilized and
enlightened gourmand, dining off that roast beef. What is that handle made of?
What but the bones of the brother of the very ox you are eating? And what do you
pick your teeth with after devouring that fat goose? with a feather of the
same fowl. And with what quill did the secretary of the Society for the
Suppression of Cruelty to Ganders formally indict his circulars? It is
only within the last month or two that that society passed a resolution to
patronize nothing but steel pens.